Guide to the Gretchen Richard Reb, 1931-2018 MS2382
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Gretchen Richard Reb papers
1931 - 2018
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Allen, Roberta Reb
Reb, Gretchen Richard
MS2382
2 Linear Feet
This collection contains correspondence, scrapbooks, photographs, artwork, and publications related to the life and especially the 1950 lobotomy of Gretchen Richard Reb. The materials date from 1931-2018.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: Personal papers, Photographs, and Publications
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Roberta Reb Allen, November 1, 2018 (2018.043)
Scope and Contents
This collection contains correspondence, scrapbooks, photographs, diaries, poetry, artwork and publications related to the life of Gretchen Richard Reb. The material dates from Circa 1931 - 2018 and includes the biography of Ms. Reb that her daughter wrote and published in 2018 titled Examined Lives
Biographical / Historical
Born in Dubuque, Iowa, Gretchen Richard (1917-1975) moved to Chicago in 1937 at the age of 20. There she enjoyed the nightlife and worked her way up in the hospitality industry to be hostess at the elegant Camellia House of the Drake Hotel. In 1942 she married Everett Reb. Their daughter Roberta was born in 1943 and, after Everett returned from World War II, their son Richard in 1947. After the birth of each child, Gretchen Richard Reb experienced periods of anxiety and paranoia, brought on in part by her sensing that her husband no longer loved her. On July 17, 1950, Dr; Walter Freeman performed a transorbital lobotomy on her. Subsequent to the lobotomy, Gretchen Reb had periods of psychosis and was institutionalized at the Independence Mental Health Institute in Iowa where the superintendent Max Witte helped her to eventually lead a normal life outside the institution. Transorbital lobotomy as a treatment has been entirely discredited, but throughout his lifetime Dr. Water Freeman performed the procedure thousands of times and often with extremely negative outcomes for patients and their families. After Everett divorced her in 1954, gaining custody of the children, Gretchen lived in Iowa, visited by her children, until her death in 1975.
Frontal lobotomy; Women -- History; Psychosurgery; Allen, Roberta Reb; Freeman, Walter
- Personal papers, 1931 - circa 1951; Series 1
  Arrangement
  Arranged loosely chronological
  Scope and Contents
  Series contains diaries, scrapbooks, correspondence, art work and poetry created and collected by Gretchen Richard Reb. This material dates from 1931-Circa 1951.
  - Gretchen Richard Reb autograph book, 1931-1934; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 5 year diary kept by Gretchen Richard Reb, 1933-1936; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Book of poetry and comments by Gretchen Richard Reb [1/3], 1933; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Book of poetry and comments by Gretchen Richard Reb [2/3], Circa 1935-1960; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Book of poetry and comments by Gretchen Richard Reb [3/3], Circa 1935-1960; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Baby book kept by Gretchen Richard Reb for daughter Roberta, Circa 1943; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letters before lobotomy, 1944-1950; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Letters after lobotomy, 1950; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Letters after 1951 [1/2], Circa 1951; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Letters after 1951 [2/2], Crica 1951; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Poem by Everett Reb, Undated; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Art work by Gretchen Richard Reb before lobotomy, Undated; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Art work by Gretchen Richard Reb after lobotomy, Undated; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Art work by Gretchen Richard Reb after lobotomy, Undated; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Scrapbook, Circa 1935; Series 1 (Box 4, Item 1)
  - Scrapbook, Circa 1940; Series 1 (Box 4, Item 2)
  - Fashion illustration by Gretchen Richard Reb, Circa 1930-Circa 1939; Series 1 (Box 4, Item 3)
- Photographs, Circa 1933 - Circa 1975; Series 2
  Series contains photographs of Gretchn Richard Reb, Everett Reb, Robert Reb Allen, and Richard Reb as well as other family members and friends from throughout Gretchen's life. Images date from Circa 1930-Circa 1975.
  Arranged loosely chronological.
  - Gretchen Richard Reb in Chicago, Circa 1937; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Gretchen Richard Reb and Everett Reb before and after marriage, Circa 1940; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Gretchen Richard Reb an Everett Reb: parents and me [donor] shortly after my birth, Circa 1943; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Gretchen Richard Reb and Roberta Reb Allen at different ages, Undated; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Gretchen Ricahrd Reb later in life after leaving mental institute, Circa 1950- Circa 1975; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Photographs of Gretchen, Everett, and family, Undated; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Family pics shorty before lobotomy, Circa 1945; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Scrapbook of photographs of Gretchen Richard {Reb) in Chicago, Circa 1937; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Publications, 1942-2018; Series 3
  Chronologically by date of publication.
  - Psychosurgery by Walter Freeman and James Watts, 1942; Series 3 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - The Early history of the Independence Mental Health Institute, 2012; Series 3 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Examined Lives, 2018; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 6)